National Negro Opera Company Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Music, 1879-1961, (15 folders) (Box 41-43)
  - Pritchett, Le Roy, and Jean Stor. The Leader; song for voice and piano., Manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p.; Music and words by Le Roy Pritchett and Jean Stor.; "Dedicated to our President Franklin D. Roosevelt." (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Puccini, Giacomo. Tosca. Vissi d'arte, vissi d'amore = love and music, these have I lived for, Act II; aria for voice (high) and piano. New York: G. Ricordi & Co., 1909., Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p.; Music by Giacomo Puccini; with English translation by W. Beatty-Kingston. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Ramos-Harris, Ethel. There'll be a jubilee!; voice and piano. New Kensington, Pennsylvania: Ramos-Harris Music Publishing Co., 1953., Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p.; Words and music by Ethel Ramos-Harris.; Dedicated to the Delta Sigma Theta Sorority.; Adopted at the grand convention Delta Theta Sorority, Cleveland, Ohio, December 1952.; Inscribed to Mary Cardwell Dawson from the composer. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Salter, Mary Turner. The City of Rachel; for voice and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1905., Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Music by Mary Turner Salter; words by Lisette Woodworth Reese.; [Fragile].; Two copies. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Sanderson, Wilfrid. Until; song for voice and piano. New York: Boosey & Hawkes, Inc., 1927., Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p.; Music by Wilfrid Sanderson; words by Edward Teschemacher. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Schubert, Franz. Ständchen = Serenade; duet for soprano and tenor (or alto) and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1940., Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Music by Franz Schubert; text by H. F. L. Rellstab; English text revised by Willis Wager. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Scott, Cyril. Two Pierrot pieces. No. 1. Lento; for piano. New York: Boosey & Hawkes, Inc., 1931., Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Speaks, Oley. Morning = Le Jour; song for voice and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1931., Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p.; Music by Oley Speaks; words by Frank L. Stanton, french version by Suzanne d'Astoria Jackowska. (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Stor, Jean. Vision! opus 45; song for baritone, chorus (mixed voices) and piano. [S.l.]: Jean Stor], [194-], Printed piano-vocal score; 16 p.; Music by Jean Stor; text from a poem by Robert G. Ingersoll.; Includes additional typed page containing the text. (Box-folder 42/3)
    Inscribed to Mary Cardwell Dawson by the composer, September 20, 1942.
  - Strauss, Johann. Springtime; for four-part chorus (mixed voices) and piano. Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania: John Church Co., 1893., Printed score; 12 p.; Music by Johann Strauss; words by "H. R. F".; Arranged by H. R. Palmer.; Two copies (one copy is missing pages 11-12). (Box-folder 42/3)
  - Vanderpool, Frederick W. Come, love me; song for voice and piano. New York: M. Witmark & Sons, 1921., Printed piano-vocal score; 3 p.; Music by Frederick W. Vanderpool; lyric by Elsie Jean. (Box-folder 42/4)
  - Verdi, Giuseppe. Aïda. Fu la sorte dell' armi., scene and duet, Act II; duet for soprano and mezzo-soprano and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1926., Printed piano-vocal score; 19 p.; Music by Giuseppe Verdi; edited by Max Spicker.; Fragment only (pages 3-18 missing). (Box-folder 42/4)
  - Verdi, Giuseppe. Ave Maria; song for voice and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1903., Printed piano-vocal score; 19 p.; Music by Giuseppe Verdi; English version by Theodore Baker.; Fragment only. (Box-folder 42/4)
  - Verdi, Giuseppe. Don Carlo. O don fatale; tenor or soprano voice and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1879., Printed piano-vocal score; 9 p.; Music by Giuseppe Verdi; libretto by Joseph Méry and Camille du Locle.; Includes one full page of penciled notes. (Box-folder 42/4)
  - Verdi, Giuseppe. Rigoletto. Bella figlia dell' amore = Fairest daughter of the graces, Act III; quartet (mixed voices) and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1940., Printed piano-vocal score; 19 p.; Music by Giuseppe Verdi; libretto by Francesco Maria Piave. (Box-folder 42/4)
  - Verdi, Giuseppe. Trovatore. Love, fly on rosy pinions (Miserere), Act IV; duet for soprano and tenor, chorus of men's voices and piano. Philadelphia: Oliver Ditson Company, [n.d.], Printed piano-vocal score; 15 p.; Music by Giuseppe Verdi; libretto by Salvatore Cammarano.; Two copies. (Box-folder 42/4)
  - White, Clarence Cameron. Five songs, opus 39; songs for voice and piano. New York: Sam Fox Publishing Company, 1949., Printed score; 15 p.; Music by Clarence Cameron White; texts various authors.; Autographed by the composer. (Box-folder 42/5)
  - White, Clarence Cameron. Ouanga; a Haitian opera in three acts. New York: Sam Fox Publishing Company, 1939., Printed piano-vocal score; 164 p.; Music by Clarence Cameron White; libretto by John Frederick Matheus.; The complete copy is autographed by the composer (title page).; Two copies (one copy fragmentary). (Box-folder 42/5)
  - Wooler, Alfred. Consider and hear me; sacred song for voice and piano. Philadelphia: Oliver Ditson Company, 1907., Printed score; 7 p.; Music by Alfred Wooler; text taken from Psalm XIII. (Box-folder 42/5)
  - [Unidentified compiler] [Unidentifed collection of classical songs]; sacred and secular, for voice and piano. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., [194-], Printed score; 198 p.; Fragmentary; title pages missing. (Box-folder 42/6)
  - Dett, R. Nathaniel. The Ordering of Moses; Biblical folk scene for soli, chorus and orchestra., Manuscript scripts and synopses.; Text based on Scripture and folk lore, compiled and set to music by R. Nathaniel Nett.; Typed and handwritten pages (Box-folder 43/1)
  - [Various]. Miscellaneous scripts, synopses, vocal texts and radio scripts., Manuscript scripts and synopses.; Typed and handwritten pages. (Box-folder 43/2)
- Books, 1889-1955, (8 folders) (Box 43)
  Includes books, a serial and a yearbook.
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Alabama State College. Department of Music. Tones and overtones, vol. 2, number 3, Spring 1955. Montgomery, Ala.: Alabama State College, 1955. (Box-folder 43/3)
  - Bartholomew, E. F. Relation of Psychology to Music, second edition, revised. Rock Island, Ill.: New Era Publishing Company, 1902., Inscribed by Mary L. Cardwell; annotated. (Box-folder 43/4)
  - Cole, Samuel W. New England Conservatory Course in Sight-Singing (Solfeggio). Boston: New England Conservatory of Music, 1903., Inscribed by Mary L. Cardwell; annotated. (Box-folder 43/5)
  - Cutter, Benjamin. Exercises in Harmony. Boston: New England Conservatory of Music, 1899., Inscribed by Mary Lucinda Cardwell. (Box-folder 43/6)
  - Elson, Louis C. Students' Note-Book and Syllabus of the Annual Course of Lectures in Musical History, 14th edition. Boston: New England Conservatory of Music, 1896., Inscribed by Mary L. Cardwell.; Includes 30 handwritten lectures written (by Mary L. Cardwell?) between 1919-1920. (Box-folder 43/7)
  - Lenom, Clément. Thirty Lessons in Solfeggio. Boston: New England Conservatory of Music, 1925., Annotated. (Box-folder 43/8)
  - National Council of Negro Women. Women United - Souvenir Year Book. Washington, D.C.: National Council of Negro Women, 1951., Inscriptions by Vivian Carter Mason and N. W. Maise.; Programs and announcements from the 19th annual convention (1954) laid in. (Box-folder 43/9)
  - Wade, L. T. The Quincy Course of Study in Music. Boston: Silver, Burdett & Co., Publishers, 1889., Business card pasted in: Compliments of L.T. Wade.; Inscribed by Flora M. Smith, Deposit, NY.; Several pages of notes and musical manuscripts laid in. (Box-folder 43/10)
- Realia, circa 1928-1961, (16 folders) (Box 44-62)
  275 metal print plates and blocks, and opera costumes. The metal printing plates are arranged into two subseries: the first contains 19 plates that lack backing and the second contains 256 plates with wood blocks attached as backing. The majority of the plates contain reverse photographic images of vocalists, ensembles, and operatic choruses, and were used for newspaper articles, reviews, concert programs, brochures, printed publications, and other publicity purposes. The rest of the plates contain reverse images used for box advertisments from sponsors that were published in National Negro Opera Company concert programs and brochures.
  The costumes subseries contains opera costumes worn for National Negro Opera Company productions between 1941 and 1961. The costumes are stored off-site -- consult reference staff in the Performing Arts Reading Room for more information.
  - Metal Printing Plates (without wood mounts), circa 1928-1941 (Box 44)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Mary Cardwell Dawson), circa 1928-1938 (Box-folder 44/1)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Mary Cardwell Dawson), circa 1939 (Box-folder 44/2)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Si Lita Haley), circa 1941 (Box-folder 44/3)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Cardwell Dawson Choir), Late 1930s (Box-folder 44/4)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Unidentified Chorus), undated (Box-folder 44/5)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Rebecca Anderson), undated (Box-folder 44/6)
    - Metal Printing Plate (New York Chapter, NNOC), undated (Box-folder 44/7)
    - Metal Printing Plates, undated, Two unidentified plates. (Box-folder 44/8)
    - Metal Printing Plates, undated, Two unidentified plates. (Box-folder 44/9)
    - Metal Printing Plate, undated, Unidentified. (Box-folder 44/10)
    - Metal Printing Plates (William Starks; unidentified second plate), undated, Two plates. (Box-folder 44/11)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Bernice Austin), undated (Box-folder 44/12)
    - Paper Printing Plate (Seymour Brown), undated (Box-folder 44/12)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Gertrude Johnson), undated (Box-folder 44/13)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Unidentified Chorus), undated (Box-folder 44/14)
    - Metal Printing Plate (NNOC Advertising montage), undated (Box-folder 44/15)
    - Metal Printing Plate (Cardwell Dawson Choir, Forbes Field, Pittsburgh) late 1930s (Box-folder 44/16)
  - Metal Printing Plates (with wood block mounts), circa 1928-1961, Contains 256 wood-backed metal printing plates. (Box 44-62)
  - Opera Costumes, circa 1941-1950s, Costumes are stored offsite - consult reference staff in the Performing Arts Reading Room for more information. (Box Off-site storage)
- La Julia Rhea Gift, 1930s-1989, (15 folders) (Box 63, 67)
  Includes autobiographical and biographical material, a large clippings page, scrapbooks containing clippings documenting Rhea's vocal career, and a 1943 Town Hall concert program.
  - Autobiographical article, circa 1950 see also Correspondence: Rhea, La Julia see also Photographs: Rhea, La Julia (Box-folder 63/1)
  - Biographical publication, circa 1970, Inscribed to Wayne Shirley (Library of Congress Music Division music specialist) by Rhea. (Box-folder 63/2)
  - Clippings, February 26, 1986, Chicago Tribune article that details Rhea's career. (Box 67)
  - Program, November 9, 1943 (Box-folder 63/3)
  - Scrapbooks, 1930s-1980s (Box-folder 63/4-7)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 63/8)
- Walter M. Dawson Papers, 1925-1970, (15 folders) (Box 64, 66)
  Walter M. Dawson was Mary Cardwell Dawson's husband. These materials primarily relate to his career as a master electrician from around 1930 to 1968. Walter Dawson was the NNOC's publicity chairman, and later served as the organization's comptroller. Items include address books, diplomas, awards, certificates, clippings, correspondence, contract forms, his obituary, publications related to the electrical trade, including a copy of the proposed 1963 Washington, D.C. Electrical Code, realia such as 1950s-1960s metal buttons and name badges, and a 1941-1943 Timeshift record book.
  Arranged by type of item or subject.
  - Address books, circa 1952-1963, Two books. (Box-folder 64/1-2)
  - Association of Electricians, Metropolitan Washington, D.C. Various materials, 1957-1964 (Box-folder 64/3)
  - Business cards, work cards, 1939, undated (Box-folder 64/4)
  - Calendar, 1926 (Box-folder 64/5)
  - Certificates, Awards, Diploma, 1925, 1930, 1963-1968, Box 66 contains Mr. Dawson's college diploma, dated 1925. (Box-folder 64/6, 66/7)
  - Clippings, 1940, 1955-1962 (Box-folder 64/7)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1942, 1962-1966 see also Correspondence: Dawson, Walter M., Includes a letter (dated January 23, 1940) signed by Senator Joseph F. Guffey, Pennsylvania, a member of the U.S. Senate Finance Committee. (Box-folder 64/8)
  - Dawson Electric Contracting Company. Contracts, 1962, undated, Most are blank forms while there is one example of a contract for specified work. (Box-folder 64/9)
  - Electrician Trade Publications, 1970 (Box-folder 64/10)
  - Obituary, 1970 (Box-folder 64/11)
  - Photographs,1925, 1927, 1934, 1941-1964, undated see Photographs: Dawson, Walter M. see Photographs: Dawson, Mary Cardwell - with others see Photographs: Pigskin Club of Washington, D.C. see Photographs: Interdenominational Ushers Union (church ushers organization) see Photographs: Handy, W. C., Other images of Walter M. Dawson can be found throughout the various group photographs of the various NNOC/NNOF Guilds and committees.
  - Realia, 1950s-1960s, Consists of a large linen 1962 wall calendar that has six metal buttons and four name badges attached. (Box-folder 64/12)
  - Timebook. Nightshift, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 64/13)
  - Washington, D.C. Electrical Code. Draft, 1963 (Box-folder 64/14)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 64/15)